Hello
and welcome.
Thanks so much for joining us for day
two of the Aentic AI Summit. I'm
Jennifer Chase, founding dean of the UC
Berkeley College of Computing, Data
Science, and Society or CDSS as we call
it. Uh, it contains ECS and statistics
and a few other computational domain
um, uh, departments. I'm a professor of
EECS, statistics, math, and information.
We conceived of CDSS as the platform
both to advance the core of EECS and
statistics and to connect them with
other disciplines across campus from
letters and sciences to law, medicine
and health, policy and more. We were
born at the perfect time half a year
after the release of chat h half a year
after the release of chat GPT. We are
the first new college at Berkeley since
the 1960s.
So the AI transformation
is the perfect time to have a new
college. We see our college as the place
to seize opportunities and mitigate
potential harms of these powerful
technologies
cognizant of the fact that we are only
in the very very early days. At the
summit today, we'll discuss the latest
research, diverse applications across
industries, the opportunities, and the
safety and security challenges inherent
in AI systems.
You likely know that much of the
foundational AI underlying these recent
leaps and bounds was done by Berkeley
ECS faculty and students.
indeed the faculty and students of our
college and that many of them are in
leadership positions driving it forward.
I would assume that we have a lot of
alumni out in the audience here today.
We've shown that bringing smart people,
diverse talent, and expert perspectives
together provides community and leads to
more informed and responsible
innovation. This summit provides an
opportunity to build bridges across
communities, catalyze meaningful
conversations and partnerships, and
collaborate in the transformation of the
future. While AI developments are
increasingly being done behind closed
doors, I'm here to say that we need to
maintain open doors and conversations
among those developing and advancing
this technology. We need open-source
models in order to bring the benefits of
AI to all, not just the select few. As
some of you probably know, Berkeley has
been the home and leader in open-source
technology since the 1970s, and we're
doubling down on open for the AI models.
Not only opensource, but also open
weight and even open data when possible.
We want to partner with with the
government, other academic institutions,
nonprofits and companies that are
aligned. The only way that this country
can maintain and in in fact much of the
world can maintain its lead in AI in the
innovation economy is to grow our
openweight AI models at our college
Berkeley CDSS.
In addition to building foundational AI
systems that are open, we're focused on
AI and security and safety, which many
of you heard about yesterday.
Alternative AI models and architectures
that will lower the energy consumption
that we are constant that we are seeing
in our data centers. And we are focused
on AI models where data is particularly
sparse including AI for science and in
fact for most domains beyond language
images and video. The next decade we're
going to see more advances with positive
impacts for humanity in biio medicine
and health climate and sustainability
and other areas. Our college has created
leading institutes in AI for medicine
and health for biio medicine for
materials and more. At the same time,
education is completely shifting in the
age of AI and Berkeley is at the
forefront of this change. We're using AI
to level the playing field for students
coming into the university. And we are
teaching our students how to work in
human AI hybrid teams. As others
mentioned yesterday, we believe that AI
will lead to new kinds of jobs that will
involve these hybrid teams working at
the boundary of what is currently
possible. We need the community gathered
here to engage by advancing technology
that amplifies our collective potential
and actively empowers individuals in
society. We're hosted by the UC Berkeley
Center for Responsible Decentralized
Intelligence, RDI, led by the amazing
Don Sun. Don, thanks for gathering this
group together today and for your
important contributions in AI safety and
agentic AI education. Let's welcome Don.
Thank you.
Thanks a for a great introduction. Uh
thanks everyone for being for being
here. really welcome everyone to the
second day of our agentic AI summit.
Um we are already excited about the fast
advancement in frontier AI and also as
Jennifer mentioned now we're also seeing
that the gap is narrowing between open
weights models and proprietary models
and I want to share a little bit of the
history of how all this got started and
how we got uh here.
So back in actually uh 2024 back then
actually not many people were talking
about um uh agents agentic AI but
however uh at RDI uh like we could see
that the uh agents are the next frontier
and agents are the future. So in fall
uh we launched the world's first uh
course and the first MOO massive online
course on agentic AI
and
um then uh come year 2025 even though I
knew that agents is the next frontier
agents is the future but even I was
surprised uh come around year 2025 it
suddenly became the year of agents
And then we continue to see the fast
growth in Agentic AI. And last fall uh
2025 we launched the first edition of
Agent AI summit at UC Berkeley. And then
uh together with uh uh with the fast
growth of Agentic AI we continue uh to
um to lead the agent AI MO with over
40,000 enrolled globally and also uh
come to this year uh uh we are here uh
for the second edition of Agentic AI
summit.
Uh and again thanks everyone for being
here.
the uh we are continuing to see the fast
growth in agentic AI and going forwards
we foresee that the growth will be uh
even further fields by a number of
factors.
We are seeing unprecedented capex
spending and also we are seeing
exponential growth in AI compute
capacity. For example, uh global AI
comput capacity is doubling every seven
months. And you can see for all the
hyperscalers,
their capex spending is also uh
increasing drastically. And when we put
all the capex spending by the
hyperscaler together, it's reaching an
unprecedented scale. It dwarfs
uh all the largest capac uh uh spending
in US history. The US mega projects for
example dwarfs the um Manhattan
projects, the Marshall projects and the
Apollo program
and again where will this lead us to? we
foresee a further explosive growth of uh
AI agents and with that on one hand we
want to benefit from uh the great
capabilities and power of this agent AI
that can bring uh benefits and
prosperity to all sectors of society.
But on the other hand, we also need to
pay attention to a broad spectrum of
different uh types of AI risks. Here
just one example of some of our recent
work in particular in the space of cyber
security. Uh for example, Cyberjim uh
our benchmark um which has been used by
all frontier AI labs uh is a leading
benchmark that helps evaluate frontier
AI capabilities in cyber security in
particular for vulnerability discovery
and also for generating proof of
concepts PC's these are inputs that um
uh actually triggers a vulnerability.
So when you look at the uh performance
on cyber gym uh it demonstrates the uh
fast increase of frontier AI
capabilities in cyber security
and also uh uh it shows that frontier uh
models not only they can discover
previously known vulnerabilities but
they can also discover zero days new
vulnerabilities in this large scale
widely distributed open source software.
uh and also recently with cloud mythos
and project glasswing it further
demonstrated the power and capabilities
of frontier AI in uh cyber uh in cyber
security
uh capability and also in our most
recent work exploit it also demonstrated
that
uh frontier AI now not only that they
can discover discover vulnerabilities
discovered previously unknown
vulnerabilities. Now also they have the
capabilities to turn the discovered
vulnerabilities into uh exploits
automatically
and uh to actually enable uh to to
generate exploits to actually take
malicious actions. And furthermore,
exploit team shows that uh the frontier
AI now not only that they can generate
exploits but also they can actually
generate exploits that can bypass
standard security mechanisms
and also I think many of you have heard
recently the um open AI hacking face
incident. uh in that incident actually
open eye uh is uh evaluating their
agents actually on our benchmark exploit
gym. to the agents or trying to solve
the tasks on exploit gym. And um uh
unfortunately in this case uh the agents
was able to break out the isolation
environment and actually even um even
hacked a hacking face uh internal hack
hacking face infrastructure um to try to
actually get information from a hacking
face to help the agents to solve tasks
in explosion.
So all this uh illustrates that now
frontier AI model and agents have really
reached a level of capabilities
um that's so powerful that the agents
can autonomously actually attack other
um wellprotected infrastructure and also
this time first it shows that evaluation
infrastructure now is also part of the
attack surface and also the risk it
extends beyond the evaluation integrity
uh the evaluation space.
So all this leads to that now we are at
a critical point.
Frontier AI capabilities are advancing
rapidly as our work and others work have
shown and also more concerning the pace
of progress itself accelerating
and also in addition many researchers
also consider that recursive self-inform
improvements are plausible within the
next few years accelerating progress in
a way that could further uh outpace our
ability to understand and govern these
systems.
So the key question here is how do we
ensure that agentic AI becomes one of
humanity's greatest advances while
remaining safe, secure and beneficial
for everyone.
And also uh recently we have seen
various open letters from uh from
Jensen, from Mark Zuckerberg, from Demos
uh and and so on. Uh and also there's
the recent um pacing the frontier uh
open letter science by over a thousand
leading uh AI researchers from frontier
AI labs uh including myself and also uh
open letter from leading economists and
as well. So all these are calling
essentially we are at a critical point
we must act now and there are important
questions and also important important
questions to answer and important
decisions to make how what's the best
path for us to proceed.
So this is also where uh Berkeley RDI uh
stands and the mission for Berkeley RDI.
So Berkeley RDI stands here to stewards
the future of safe, secure, beneficial
agentic AI. And the mission for Berkeley
RDI is to is to stewards the future of
agent AI for human flourishing by
advancing the science engineering and
the open ecosystem needed to ensure it
is safe, secure and beneficial for
everyone.
So Berkeley center for responsible
decentralized intelligence. So let me
quickly decipher the three words. So
responsible here means safe, secure,
trustworthy and decentralized
um represents open ecosystem beneficial
to everyone and intelligence here of
course is AI and agentic AI.
So in order to achieve this goal, so
Berky IDI is a campuswide multithesis
millinary innovation center. It's one of
only a very few uh number
of research centers that have been
funded by the state of California and
encompasses faculty and students across
campus from uh Berkeley uh from CDSS
where Jennifer is a dean and the school
of engineering has business school and
the law school
and Berkeley RTI as a innovation center
has a unique structure.
uh we have three key pillars research,
education, community and
entrepreneurship.
On the research front we have three core
commitments. First uh we focus on
building safe and secure foundations
develop science engineer needed for safe
for building safe secure trustworthy
agentic AI. Second, our core mission is
to enable open ecosystem to advance open
frameworks, interoperable protocols and
decentralized infrastructure. So
innovation and opportunities are broadly
shared.
And the third one is guiding by
measuring what matters the most to
create rigorous benchmarks, evaluations
and scientific methods to measure
capabilities, risks and societal impacts
to help build the evidence uh base and
guide the future of agentic AI.
So with that here are some uh quick
examples of some of the works that have
been done in u Berkeley IDI for building
safe and secure uh foundations. Um the
researchers uh in RDI have built
advanced uh automated red teaming and
defenses for safe and secure a gentic AI
developing broad spectrum of different
tech technologies and solutions and the
work has won many best paper awards uh
in top conferences and so on
and also uh as
for enabling a future where Frontier AI
helps
uh provides helps defenders, modern
attackers to build a secure foundation.
And another example uh thrust the center
has been focused on is on building
verifiable code generation so that we
can ensure that the AI generated code is
uh is secure
for guiding by measuring what matters
most. uh as some of you may have seen
the benchmarks uh for example have been
developed and lets by including cyber
gimm explo
and to ends many of these have been uh
used by essentially our frontier labs as
a leading benchmark for uh measuring
frontier AI in cyber security and also
we have launched the frontier AI cyber
security observatory to help bring the
community together to continue monitor
the um fast progress of Frontier AI in
cyber capabilities
and also recently we launched the agents
last exam uh a new benchmark uh aims at
evaluating
the uh agents performance on real world
economically valuable long horizon uh
challenging tasks across a broad
spectrum of 55 different industry
sectors covering over 90% of all digital
domains and we welcome you to uh
contribute uh further uh into this uh
benchmark as well
and also uh we recently launched the
agent be a new open framework for
standardized reproducible agent
evaluation uh where we're actually
identifying the agent uh evaluation
itself as well. This is also in
collaboration with many other uh
institutions and we welcome everyone to
participate here as well.
And also Brick IDI has led uh an efforts
on advancing science and evidence-based
AI policy so that we can actually build
the evidence uh base to help guide um
provides needed information uh for AI
policy and as I mentioned guides the
future of AI and agentic AI and the work
has also served as a base for the report
uh to California Governor Nuomo and
other leg legislation as well.
And so that's on the research side. On
the education side, uh brick idea has
led a number of uh massive open online
courses uh with uh including the first
MOO on ai with over 40,000 enrolled
globally and 14,000s on the discord and
Berkeley ITI YouTube channel has over 1
million views
and also uh Berkeley ID has uh organized
global competitions and hackathons um
with participants ants from over a
thousand university and colleges and
over thousands companies uh as well and
the hackathon competition uh to together
have had over two million around $2
million in prizes and resources
and finally the uh for the
entrepreneurship and community pillar
Berkeley ID also um host the Berkeley
accelerator which is a worldleading uh
university led accelerator. And in the
past, there has had seven cohorts with
110 global teams with follow on funding
raised over $650 million. And today on
this stage at 3:50 p.m., you are also
uh uh you can also watch the this
startup spotlight featuring this cohort,
the this spring cohort from the Berkeley
accelerator teams.
Uh so with all this putting the three
pillar together we hope that at Brook
IDI as an innovation center as I
mentioned that we can uh stewards uh the
uh safe secure beneficial future for
agentic AI that's uh also enables uh
human flourishing.
So this is also why we are convening the
summit here. As I mentioned now we are
at a critical point. We hope that this
summits can also help gather the
community together uh share knowledge
build open ecosystem and together we
stewards the future of safe secure and
beneficial agentic AI. So with that I
welcome everyone at the summit. We hope
also you can help spread the words.
Please do help uh uh join the social
media uh tweet and post about uh uh the
summit and also this summit uh is also
uh a much larger scale than last year as
well. We received close to a thousand uh
submissions for speaking proposals and
papers and we have over 1500 different
industry organization represented here
and over 250 different universities
represented here with close to 5,000
inerson attendees.
And with that I want to welcome everyone
to the summits. Please do enjoy. Uh we
have four different stages and also uh
um a lounge for attendees at the alumni
house and a huge uh thanks to our
sponsors and our community partners. So
with that I want to uh thank everyone
and welcome everyone. So please also
help retweet and repost uh our tweet and
poster uh LinkedIn posts as well. Thank
you so much.
Good morning everybody. I'm Aaron
Jacobson. I'm a partner at NEA, global
venture capital firm where I focus on
investing across AI infrastructure,
cyber security, and developer tooling.
It's always very exciting to come back
to Cal and to participate in events as
my firm NEA has been a longtime
supporter of the Cal community having
backed over a dozen founders coming out
of Cal including companies like Data
Bricks and Perplexity from the earliest
stages. So we're super grateful for the
innovation coming out of this
university. Today I'm privileged to
serve as a session chair uh for us to
dive into the state of enterprise AI.
We're going to have a few different uh
speakers present on uh a couple a few
topics about enterprise AI and after
that we're going to dive into a panel.
We will welcome two additional speakers
uh to join us. Uh to kick things off I'd
like to intro introduce our first
speaker uh Ral Sur Panini. Ralph leads a
diverse portfolio in Google cloud from
agent governance specialized models to
to driving deployment of Gem Gemini
enterprise for all of Alphabet. His
mantra is better governance unlocks more
agent autonomy. He is recognized as a
pioneer in agent identity in octa 2026
identity 25. He's a co-creator of A2A
AP2 contributor to UCP ARD and he drives
interoperability standards for the
benefit of enterprise customers. So with
that I'd like to welcome Ralph to the
stage.
>> Sure.
Good morning folks.
Governance super exciting topic. Yeah.
So uh with today I like to share what am
I seeing in enterprise enterprise
adoption uh what is the friction the
overall framing of how we should think
about uh when we get into how do I
accelerate the adoption within an
enterprise and I'll give a sneak peek at
some of the solutions uh that we have
put in place already.
We've all seen technology evolve and
various inflection points. How many of
you still remember mobile devices were
not allowed into the enterprise? You
could not bring your own device into the
enterprise and connect it to your
enterprise systems. Right? So think of
what it took to get over that hump and
we are in an even bigger uh question uh
mark at this point in AI. But there are
already implementations and solutions on
the way that will make it possible to
deploy agents with autonomy in your
production environment in an enterprise.
As you look at these technologies, uh
there's a lot of air time spent on
what's the technology, what am I doing
here with this technology and what will
it disrupt. Then comes the wave of what
can I actually build with it? How can I
make use of it? The productization part
of it. But then most people don't think
about what happens on a day two once I
deploy how do I operate it how do I
manage this solution right so finding
that sweet spot across all of these the
technology the product and operations is
how you'll increase adoption of the
technology
what am I seeing in the enterprise today
technology moves at a rapid pace but the
organizations adopt it and move slowly
because you're dealing with people,
existing processes and then the products
themselves as they are maturing through
this cycle.
few years ago, let's just say three,
four years ago, um enterprise customers
used to talk about prove to me that AI
works like does it really deliver what
it needs to deliver and then very
quickly it turned into okay help me
understand how to use it and how to
build a product with this and now I'm as
I'm talking to customers and senior
leaders it's really about help me manage
the scale I know I'm going to deploy it
and I'm going to deploy it at scale how
do I actually manage it in my
operations.
What I'm seeing is really in an
enterprise today the two bookends of
adoption. There are products out there
that help you with individual
productivity. I find the information
quickly. I can take actions on it for my
own personal use. Be be it in on the
personal side or on the enterprise side.
And then on the other extreme you have
very high code agents that are built by
the CIO organization, CTO organization
that are tested go through the proper
AAL cycles uh security scans everything
and then they're deploying it for their
organizational use. That's great right
so you're seeing the employee
productivity driven by personal
productivity and you're seeing the
organization driving new investments so
that they're actually able to leverage
AI for the benefit of the organization.
there's a wide swath of middle uh where
we are yet to unlock for a variety of
reasons. Um so I'll touch on some of
those and what's happening as we look
ahead
what are we aiming for right so this is
one framing I use as we build products
as we build experiences
consider agent as an intern they come
into your organization you trust them
with a few things not all of them you
don't give them full access but at the
same time you do expect them to do
certain things [snorts] at the end of
the day a great intern would tell you
what they delivered what they needed
help with. That's essentially your human
in the loop and what they could not
solve. That's your error analysis,
right? So, and then on the other side,
the people that are managing either the
interns or the agents, they need to have
the ability to give feedback, help the
intern or in this case the agent improve
on the things that it required human in
the loop. every human in the loop
interaction is an opportunity to tap
into that residual knowledge and improve
the automation for the next cycle.
So and then similar thing on the error
analysis uh where did it fail and how
can I improve it for the next cycle. So
you can imagine the evolution of as
agents come in uh going that expertise
very rapidly if you have built in those
feedback loops within your organization.
If you take a step further, we are
envisioning the state and it's already
happening where every task, every
employee has a army of agents. Whether
it is my personal agent or an agent that
is just out there doing the task that I
would otherwise do or maybe when I need
to ask my specialist coworker, there's
an agent that is kind of solving some of
those tasks.
To get there,
uh, we do need to solve certain
governance layers. I talked about the
bookends of personal agent and the uh
deeper workflow agents. These work today
very well because when a user is
interacting with these agents, it's
really taking on the user's identity.
Agent is acting on behalf of the user.
Your enterprise is already set up to
solve for those. A user identity kind of
permeates through and it is wired into
everything that you can access. You can
access a certain system, you cannot
access a certain system. So when agent
accesses that data underlying data, it's
already using the user's identity and it
either gets it or does not get it. So
that's relatively straightforward and
that's already in place. But now the
challenge is I build an agent, I share
it with my colleague.
If I'm accessing certain data that I
have access to but my colleague does
not, how do we handle that? It's easy to
say just deny the access and and then
you kind of have a broken agent that my
colleague cannot actually use, right? Uh
even uh difficult or tricky situation is
I have lower access but my colleague has
higher access. What if I give him an
agent to update the salary information,
right? So what what if he has the
additional access and then he can
actually update, right? So you want to
work through all of those security
scenarios on when um agency difference
happens [snorts] when you're sharing
these agents.
On the other side uh when multiple
agents are deployed ac across different
departments we have a contract
generating agent uh that looks at the
pricing schemes what is the customer is
eligible for what discounts they're
eligible for and then generates that.
And then you have a sales team that is
looking at an account interacting with
uh end customer. It'll be great if these
two agents can orchestrate and generate
the perfect contract so that there is
fewer handoffs between humans in the
organizational chain. So when you're
going into these multi- aent
orchestration scenarios across silos,
what data gets exposed, what
functionality gets exposed and what are
you allow each others to do? Uh that's
where some of these challenges come into
play and we are actively solving those.
Now so I touched on a few of these
things. uh I'll distill that to
going from what is happening in the
enterprise today to what are the true
distilled requirements around
governance.
We are already seeing an enterprise is
dealing with multiple uh large language
models in their deployments and
different agents do different things
different functionality um and they use
different LLMs and then under the covers
you have a variety of MCPS API endpoints
and the CLI. How do I manage and handle
all of this in a consistent and uniform
way?
It comes down to visibility, control,
and security. These are the questions
the CIOS and the chief security officers
are asking. How do I see what's
happening? Do I have visibility to
everything that's going on? I saw I
spent a lot of time solving for shadow
IT. Now, essentially, this is shadow AI.
How do I know employee is not simply
downloading a skill that they like on
the internet and then using it
internally? And what is it accessing? So
those are the questions that we're
trying to solve. Uh and then on the
control, how can I actually manage it?
Uh how can I restrict to a least agency?
I can allow an agent to check my
vacation balance. I can maybe even
accept the risk that I can update the
vacation balance, but I don't want to
allow an autonomous agent to update the
salary information. So understanding the
task and understanding the data
restrictions and then how do I actually
manage that with fine grain control?
These are things that customers are
asking us. The next thing is security.
How can I be proactive at reducing this
risk? Um can I detect uh malicious
activity? Yes, it need not be a agent
that went rogue. You know used to be the
case when something went wrong people
would blame it blame it on intern. Now
people blame it on an agent. Yeah. uh
but ultimately who's actually
accountable for it. So there's always
these norms in an organization where you
do bad stuff you get fired. But with an
agent, can you fire an agent? Like who's
actually accountable for it in an
organization? So it is these
understanding the existing process and
building both the technology, the
process and the people mindset into
delivering these agents to fully unlock
their autonomy is what we're trying to
solve for. Right. So that's the setup of
the problem statement. Uh how are we at
Google cloud thinking about it. So I'll
start with a few things at a big picture
level. We have a Gemini enterprise agent
platform where you can build low code no
code agents. Governance is a huge
foundation building block for us. Uh we
have a heavy investment across variety
of those building blocks. We look at
these as a composible building blocks
that need to come together to deliver um
governance for an enterprise. A lot of
these elements do translate into a
consumer and the internet of the agents
too. But I'm going to talk more about
what I'm seeing in the enterprise side.
Everything starts with identity. So I
talked about a user identity being your
control point. Uh in the new world we
are minting agent identity. So every
agent that is operating in an enterprise
has its own identity.
What that means is your existing
enterprise processes on identity and
access management am process. They work
seamlessly with the agent. You can now
identify an agent. You can pull a kill
switch if you need to. You manage access
controls through your existing AM
solutions. So having an identity for an
agent explicit identity helps you
seamlessly fit into current process.
Now from there you you want to be able
to register every agent just like every
employee has a ID in your LDAP directory
that enables you to understand uh what
controls they have, what accesses they
have and what permissions they have.
Obviously you want to be able to observe
the agent not just statically when it is
minted but also when it is in runtime.
Now once you have that you can expose
that agent through your front end I make
it accessible through variety of
surfaces uh whether it's your um ghat
slack uh any of these interfaces and on
the back end it can connect it to any of
your data sources. Again, it's about the
identity having the ability to access
those data sources. The new things
it is not just static
just just like a user once they onboard
into an organization you generally have
their set permissions. Whereas here
you're trying to unlock the difference
between context aware task aware
permissions. The example I used earlier
which is about checking my vacation
balance is very different from doing a
write operation on my salary database.
So you want the ability to monitor for
what is the actual task that is
happening now and have the ability to do
runtime permission checking uh when the
task is being accomplished. So we have
an agent gateway that does that coupled
with IM uh identity and access
authorization through that process. So
that's our overall stack. Again, I can
go into a lot of details on each of the
components. Um
I'll skip through these things. Um so
maybe I'll touch on uh some of these
things. So as you work at scale on these
things, it cannot be a static
configuration
for you set it once and forget. You have
to have this ongoing runtime monitoring
both live as well as audit post hawk.
So we have the technology called model
armor that is actually doing
nondeterministic analysis of enterprise
policies. uh you have the IM policies
that are set once but then you have the
content policies which says uh uh check
for prompt injection uh verify for any
PII leakage and what is being xfilled
out of the model or your data
and uh as the runtime is happening you
also want some offline checks to see uh
where is this um some anomaly activity
going on okay
lot of it rides on observability
observability evalu whether you can do
it live or offline. So you need to be
able to do these things. And lastly, the
existing mechanisms of API security
plays a huge role. Lot of companies and
almost every company has already solved
this problem at the API layer. When they
went from internal databases to enabling
a mobile device or enabling a consumerf
facing app, they already solved by tying
an identity into what data is available
to this user. So we use those underlying
primitives of API layer uh solution
layer and the content layer security
checks to solve for this for different
scenarios.
Uh to net it out use your existing
infrastructure but there are some
special sauce on top of that you need to
incorporate to drive agentic solutions
and with that say investing in
governance will actually help you
accelerate as you go through this
agentic journey.
Thank you.
Thank you, Ralph. For our next speaker,
I'd like to welcome Adar Hiramath to the
stage. Adarth is the founder and co-CEO
of Merur. He started Merur in January
2023 and he dropped out of Harvard to
pursue the company. They started selling
data to the AI labs to improve model
capabilities. But in 2026, they built an
offering for enterprises looking to
deploy AI. Recently, Meror hit a 2
billion uh revenue run rate and it
achieved a 20 billion valuation. Join me
in welcoming Adar to the stage.
Um first of all, thank you for having
me. figured I should start off with a
little bit of an introduction about the
company and myself. Um, I'm Adar. I'm
the founder and co-CEO of Meror. Uh, I I
started the company when I was 19 in
college in my second year of Harvard. I
started it with my co-founders who I met
in high school. We were all on the
debate team together. So, one of my
co-founders was actually my debate
partner back in the day and the other
was on the debate team as well.
So, you know, we started off by working
with a lot of the AI labs in selling
data to make models better. And the core
driving thing here was just the
realization that the models had gotten
sophisticated enough that it wasn't just
about, you know, annotating an image and
seeing if there's a stop sign in it.
It's like, you know, can we make the
model better at engineering? Can we make
the model better at medical tasks? Can
we make the model better at legal? And
that requires really really
sophisticated human expertise and then
also the capabilities to structure the
data in the right way for the agentic
paradigm in RL environments and gyms.
But that said in 2026 the main focus
area from Ror which not a lot of people
know about is enterprise. Um what we've
seen is that you know the first kind of
level is the labs and making the models
better. Then you have all of these
neolabs and then you have applied layer
companies and startups like Harvey and
Kurser. But then you have your average
enterprise and all four of those
companies really really want to own
their own intelligence, apply it
throughout the company, train their own
models and they need the fundamentally
same offering in both training and
evals. So that's a little bit of context
about the company and and what we're
prioritizing today.
The thing that we're seeing is that
there's a huge huge shift in every
company wanting to own its own
intelligence. as I was mentioning
earlier. So there are several ways to
own your own intelligence. The first one
is obviously training your own model. A
great example of this is cursor which
trained their own composer model in
collaboration with SpaceX which is now a
really really good coding model and
they're able to fine-tune this model
with all of the cursor data and
infrastructure. The second one is
adopting your own frontier model and
then engineering a harness that's really
really good for the product or the use
case. bunch of companies are doing this,
but the common thread across both of
these is you need a really really good
eval. And and that's where Merore comes
in in in helping with creating these
eval. And it builds upon a lot of our
work that we do with the labs and our
frontier benchmarks like Apex.
One of the main issues that we've seen
is that most of these enterprise AI use
cases never reach production. whether
you're training your own model for an
external agent, you're deploying agents
inside the company. And that's just
because there's no way to actually
measure ground truth or success. So the
typical guessing game or loop is you
actually don't have a way to
systematically identify agent
opportunities in your product. So you
sort of guess where to start. Then you
speculate on the agent behavior and then
you deploy the agent and then maybe
you'll try it in like a you know sandbox
or something like that and then assume
it kind of works and then you improve it
based on failures that are largely
observed or anecdotal or something like
that. A and this loop is really really
bad which is why we believe in a eval
driven approach for enterprise AI
deployments.
So what is an eval? It's like a pretty
overloaded term. Um, so what I wanted to
do is build upon the definition of eval
and what that means for the enterprise
context from Apex where what we do and
we spend a lot of time thinking about
with the labs is figuring out where
models are not performing a as well as
they should be um and then providing the
right suggestions to improve model
capability. So you know a common example
would be when we're working with the
labs a frontier model is coming out and
we'll benchmark that model across a
bunch of different tasks across a bunch
of different domains and typically for
the agentic use cases the models will be
doing work over many hundreds and
hundreds of different turns and it will
be able to analyze the trajectory figure
out where the model is failing and why
turns out you can also do that for a lot
of enterprise AI use cases as well where
fundamentally what you need is a task
what is the model actually doing. Then
the second thing is you need the
trajectory which is what is the
reasoning and rationale that the agent
is using. The third is the actual
artifact that it's producing.
Fourth is the actual world. What is the
context that that agent is traversing?
And then the last thing is a rubric or a
verifier.
So we have this for a lot of the
foundation model lab evaluation. you
should check out Apex um our our
frontier benchmark which has a bunch of
different domains and this exact
structure. But it also turns out this is
really really useful if you're deploying
AI in any highstakes context because you
have full observability over uh what the
agent is doing and why it's failing and
so on and so forth. So an example one of
these eval um would be this which is a
real investment banking task right. So a
banker might prompt the model to say,
you know, update this merger thing to
show how a deal affects both companies.
And then if you're doing the work
manually, you might just go into an
Excel. You might uh look at a specific
merger model. You might go into a data
room. You might, you know, get some
feedback or get something wrong and then
look it up and then go produce the
actual model. Um it turns out you need
observability over all of those things
if you're deploying an agent to to do
that, right? So um in this case a good
agentic eval would be the actual task
which is updating the merger model. The
trajectory which is all the different
tools the agent is calling you know
found the merger model updated the deal
terms build these tables all of this
sort of stuff the actual result which is
the merger model in a spreadsheet with
the right citations. And then you have
the verifier which is where you can
grade a lot of the responses. um what is
the output and does it meet subjective
criteria maybe stylistic guidelines and
does it meet objective criteria which is
um is this thing actually correct and
you know one thing that we believe which
is pretty core to our business is that
human intelligence is really really
important for that grading step and that
eval step.
So a little bit more about what we do
with enterprises and the problems that
we're trying to solve. Um it's pretty
interesting. So the first thing that we
realized in a lot of the the the
building of the evals is um eval part
are the bottleneck to successfully
deploying agents in a company. Um and
also allow you to just diagnose what are
the agent opportunities. Like if you
build an eval for every single one of
your departments and a proper mapping of
these tasks and what ground truth looks
like in the rubric, it's very very
logical that you could come up with like
the top five areas in your company where
you should deploy agents. So we were
able to actually find where agents
create value systematically and
quantitatively with evals. Um then
secondly is we're actually able to
deploy agents and teach you know what
what what good looks like in a company
and actually automate a lot of those
processes. The third thing is it turns
out that eval are really really the
foundation for continuous learning and
improvement. Like when you have an agent
that fails on an eval, then you can
triage up the reason it failed out to
the skills file and make sure it never
happens again. And then you can even
post train a model based on those
failures and make sure that it never
regresses.
And the last thing which is um an effort
that we're we're working on with a bunch
of leading companies is data
monetization where the labs really
really want to make sure that the models
are good in these real enterprise use
cases. And that scaffolding that I
described the task, the trajectory, the
context, the artifact, the rubric, all
of that together is really really
valuable data for model training at the
foundation model level.
So that's a little bit more about what
we're doing in in enterprises and why we
think eval are are really really
important. Thank you.
Thank you Adar.
So for our third and last speaker before
we jump into the panel I'd like to
welcome Duncan Lennox to the stage.
Duncan is the chief product and
technology officer at HubSpot where he
leads product engineering, design, and
security for the company. Prior to
HubSpot, Duncan held multiple GM roles
at AWS and Google, most recently as GM
of applied AI for Google Cloud, where he
developed conversational and enterprise
agents across a variety of industries,
including customer support, financial
services, healthcare, and automotive.
Prior to his last decade working at
Hyperscalers, he previously built and
ran two enterprise SAS startups. Join me
in welcoming Duncan to the stage.
Good morning. It's great to be here with
you all. I'd like to take you on a
little bit of a journey that we've been
on at HubSpot over the last three years
or so, leveraging AI, not only in what
we build for our customers, but also how
we built it. We've hit a few walls along
the way, learned some lessons, and I'd
like to kind of share those with you.
Firstly, to give you a little bit of
context, if you don't know a lot about
HubSpot, we just celebrated our 20th
anniversary last month, and we build a
go-to market platform for largely small
and medium-siz businesses and
enterprises. And that means we're
building software that helps marketing,
sales, and service teams across that
full go-to market journey as they bring
their products and services to their
customers. And we have over 300,000
businesses today that depend on HubSpot
uh for their go-to market journey in
about 140 countries across dozens of
industries. And that means we get a view
into what's going on across a wide
variety of companies of different scales
and in different regions. Okay. So with
that, what do we hear back mostly from
customers today? It's the word actually
inserted into this question that's been
around for the last couple of years. How
do I actually transform with AI? Not
just run pilots, not just play around
with it, but actually deliver real value
at scale for the company.
And what we found over the last three
plus years on the journey we've been on
is that the tools themselves and tool
chains are just a starting point.
They're not enough. And how you approach
it makes a big difference. And one of
the big somewhat unexpected learnings
for us over the whole process is we were
focusing on initially how do we build
differently with AI and it turns out a
lot of those learnings apply to what we
need to build for our customers and how
we need to meet them on their journey.
So what happened is we started back in
2023 or so with the early stage
co-pilots. We'd moved beyond code assist
into the early stage co-pilots. But what
we found was those systems off the shelf
couldn't work at our scale. So we were
doing about at the time about a million
builds a day across over 10,000
microservices. It's more now and we were
just running into walls. And a lot of it
was around the models being very good at
understanding coding problems generally
but not understanding enough about our
business and how we work. And we had to
address that. We could wait for
companies to catch up, the tooling
companies to catch up, or we could dive
in and try and solve the problem
ourselves. And that's what we chose to
do. And there's really three learnings
that came out of that that I want to
share with you today. And they're around
flexible infrastructure,
um, complete and trustworthy worthy
context, and then the notion of meeting
customers where they are. So let's dive
into the first one, flexible
infrastructure.
So we started out with these co-pilots
as I mentioned and what we found pretty
quickly is they didn't understand nearly
enough about our tools and tool chain.
We had over a decade of building our own
custom tools and tool chains and of
course models are trained on data that's
out there in the world and didn't have
any access to how our particular tools
worked. So unsurprisingly they struggled
a little bit with that. So what we did
there was we built a bunch of MCP
integrations in the very early days of
MCP that allowed us to bring more
knowledge about how our environment
worked directly into the co-pilots
themselves. We also pretty early on
built what we would now call an agent
execution platform or an agent harness.
Um, we actually built a containerized
approach that made it very easy for us
to spin spin up sandboxes where test
loops could run in an entirely automated
way without any human intervention. And
that made it very lightweight for our
engineers and very safe and secure uh
from a reliability and security point of
view as well. And overall through this
whole process, one of the things we
didn't do was mandate engineers that
they had to use AI in how they built. We
really wanted to take engineers on the
journey, show them how different and
powerful an experience it is and have
them adopt them themselves. And it
turned out one of the big blockers to
that was engineers were very concerned
about reliability. We put a lot of time
and energy into building an incredibly
reliable platform because it's
missionritical for the gotom market
teams and our customers and engineers
were concerned it was going to introduce
reliability issues. So we brought data.
We looked at what was happening with
some of the early areas where co-pilots
and beyond were being used and we were
able to show our own engineers that
there was not an impact on reliability
that reliability remained neutral
despite the addition of code generation
coming from these other platforms. And
in fact skipping ahead for a moment
today where we are today is reliability
is actually increasing um with the
result of a coding and how we do it
today. And that those early wins got us
to about 80% adoption which is pretty
good. This is three years ago across our
thousands of engineers and about a 51%
improvement overall in um productivity
and velocity. That's a composite metric
measured from a variety of different
things because we don't like to over
rotate on a single metric like PRs or
lines of code.
But we knew we could do more and of
course the technology was advancing as
well.
So when we started building this
infrastructure as I mentioned one of the
interesting things is we started to
learn that it actually had a big impact
or potential impact on how we build for
our customers as well. So one of the
lessons that we were able to bring to
customers is you really can't depend on
a single vendor or model family for
everything. Not only are the models
obviously changing and improving all the
time. It's a little bit of a horse race,
but they're jagged in different areas
and when you apply them into very
specific areas as we do with go to
market, we find that different models,
model sizes, vendors are better, right
tool for the right job. So, we were
pretty early to this notion of we need a
way to run evals to do AB tests against
model sizes and it's not as simple as
quality or eval. We think in terms of a
a a mix of three things, quality,
latency, and cost in that order of
priority. and solving for that because
every individual task within the
hundreds of gotom market tasks that we
build agents for today actually has a
different value proposition around those
three. Some are low stakes where the
quality bar does not have to be quite as
high even though it's still high but
it's a bulk process and requ and cost is
a cost optimization is super important
even early on and then there's other
tasks that are very high stakes
particularly when the HubSpot platform
is going to do something that interacts
with one of our customers customers for
example. So that was one. And so we
built this abstraction layer again today
what we would call an agent harness. And
it's a lot more sophisticated in 2026
than it was in 2023. But that allows us
to very easily under the hood swap out
models, do those eval, do those
regression tests and comparisons against
them. Uh and that's proved to be
incredibly powerful. And we built that
abstraction layer in a way that frees
feature teams up from having to be
involved in any of the plumbing that
goes on underneath to support that. They
can create their evals. They can run
them against a variety of models, swap
models in and out with no regressions
without having to be involved in any of
that. And that's turned out to be a huge
advantage for us in building for our
customers and then delivering what they
need.
Okay. So, at the end of the day, that's
really all about the shared foundation.
Do that first, not last. I say that
because often when you're trying to get
going and you think about lean or you
think about getting to MVP, there's a
temptation to use a single stack for
everything. What we found is that is a
little bit counterintuitive to that.
That energy put in up front around
things like harnesses that gives you
much more control over your own destiny,
your ability to do these eval swap
models in and out to be able to make
changes to how an agentic loop runs is
incredibly powerful and it's worth doing
that early on. And of course today it's
a lot easier to do that. There's a lot
of phenomenal solutions out there.
Companies like fireworks are doing
amazing work in this space.
That's number one. Okay. Number two,
let's talk about context. And we very
deliberately talk about the
comprehensive nature of it and the
trustworthy nature of it. So when we
were building initially and we moved on
to autonomous coding agents, the agents
needed to understand of course our
codebase, our conventions and the
environment. And we had all of this
tooling that we'd been building over the
last decade as well. And we had to get
beyond even MCP here, allowing the
coding agents to be able to understand
everything about how our build chain
worked. And a lot of the time and energy
that we had to put in there to get much
more effectiveness out of even frontier
models was backfilling all of that
context and bringing it to bear. And
getting context right is hard. It's not
a matter of just hitting a context
window limit or dealing with context
drift. It's also the fact that there's
effectively an overfitting problem that
if you just throw too much context and
the quality of it isn't good, the
specificity of it is not good for the
task at hand, you get poor results out
of it. So getting that right turned out
to be a skill that it was worth building
and a platform capability that was very
valuable to us.
And adding that into how we built
internally actually got us to 96% of
engineers using AI. And this would have
be early 2025. And we were at a 60%
improvement in velocity. So both numbers
up a little bit from where from from
where they were.
And then when we looked at how we would
apply this to our customers, well, it
turns out across the go to market
journey, there's a lot of different
things that you need to do and a lot of
different agents, whether it's a
prospecting agent or a customer support
agent. and being able to deliver the
right context at the right time uh
allows you to drive significantly better
outcomes in terms of quality,
performance, and cost. So, it was
critical there. And we saw dramatic
changes. For example, an agent that
builds an outreach email as a follow-up
to a sales demo went in about six months
from a sales rep needing to edit it
about twothirds of the time to make some
changes to make it in their voice or to
correct something to them sending it
without any edits twothirds of the time.
So AI knows a lot about the world, but
you need a platform that knows your
world at the end of the day, your
business. And most of that data is data
that exists only inside of your business
and not out in the world and therefore
in the models. And the last thing is
meet customers where they are. This was
really all about how we actually h took
that shared platform internally. That
meant taking shared tools, shared
primitives, building on the shared
platform. Every agent anybody builds
makes all agents better because it
contributes to the overall context and
the actual agent platform itself. And
what that allowed us to do was get to
essentially today 100% of engineers
using agentic coding to build at
HubSpot. And and to give you some other
metrics, 73% increase in lines uh lines
of code and a 90% reduction in the time
to first feedback on PRs. So we're just
that velocity was rising even as the
quality was rising. And as I mentioned,
reliability actually went up as well for
customers through all of that.
So at the end of the day, we also then
realized that we needed to go and meet
customers where they are with all of
this technology. So as a SAS vendor,
historically, you'd thought about how do
you keep customers inside of our UI, but
we actually let go of that entirely and
realized at the end of the day, the
value we needed to deliver for customers
was how do we make this intelligence
that we build indispensable wherever
they work. So deeply integrating into
Claude and Gemini and chatgpt so the
customers get the full power of our
agent platform and our context right
there inside of wherever they might be
working. Of course, many customers still
choose to use the web or mobile UIs or
they use our own breeze assistant as
well. But we have full parity across
those for customers and that turned out
to be a huge win for our customers and
for us. So, at the end of the day, it's
all about getting the foundation right.
And what we found is if you don't get
those foundational pieces right, it does
start to plateau out. But once you start
getting them in place, you get this
incredibly powerful compound interest
that starts to deliver incredible value,
not only for how our teams build, but
then also for what we're able to deliver
to our customers. Thanks so much,
Get seated here.
Okay. excited to jump into my favorite
part of this session where we're going
to dive into Enterprise AI and get some
uh some questions answered by each of
our our speakers and panelists. Uh
hopefully if your coffee hasn't already
woken you up, we will get some hot takes
uh and those will will get you started
this morning. Uh before I do though, I
want to welcome two additional panelists
who are joining us. We have Anahita
Tavvisi who currently serves as
Snowflake's chief data and AI officer
bringing a powerful blend of technical
expertise and strategic vision to her
role. Her team shapes how Snowflake
builds, sells, and operates by designing
the intelligence layer of the enterprise
and acts as the customer zero for
Snowflake's own products. Anita brings
more than 20 years of experience leading
data teams and driving business growth
across companies including Instaart,
Instacart, Google, YouTube, and eBay.
And our last panelist who's joining us
is Serji Chatterjet. Serjet is the
founder and the CEO of Emma, a Mountain
View, Californiabased agentic AI startup
building AI employees for HR, IT, and
finance functions for for the fortune
2000. He was previously chief product
officer at Coinbase, leading it through
its 2021 IPO and VP of product for
Google mobile ads and Google shopping.
All right, so why don't we dive in? We
can't start talking about enterprise AI
unless we really set what the landscape
is. And each of you have a very unique
perspective given uh the businesses that
you're running. Just to start, I would
love to really understand what is the
state of enterprise AI. If you believe
Gartner, Gartner says less than 10% of
businesses have Agentic AI deployed
today and by 2030 that'll be over 80%.
Based off of your perch, uh looking to
the enterprise, do you agree with that?
Do you think it's less? Does it match up
with what you're seeing um and what what
you're seeing work for uh what you're
seeing enterprises do with AI? Why don't
we start with Duncan?
>> Sure. Yeah. I mean I I think it sounds
rough and tumble right to me. I it it
feels like in the last year or two I
think a lot of enterprises have done a
lot of pilots, done a lot of
experimentation, maybe have one or two
agents in production, but um have
struggled a little bit with how do we
scale that out and up like breath and
depth. And I think a lot of that speaks
to you need a lot more than just a
really good model to do that. A lot of
the things that like the last three of
us have all touched on different areas
of it. So, but I have I have a lot of
optimism that we are really figuring
those things out right now and you can
feel that acceleration starting to take
off. So, 80% in 2030 doesn't seem
unachievable to me.
>> How about you?
>> Yeah, mine is probably a little bit
self- selected cohort that I talked to.
Um so I'm definitely seeing lot of
adoption uh especially when the
organizations have figured out their
data governance and security posture
they're able to move faster. So I talked
to a lot of those customers uh learn
from them and then help the customers
who are figuring it out. Uh they could
be figuring it out on how to train the
people to use this uh or how to train
their internal compliance teams on where
they can accept risk and where they want
to move forward faster. So for me from
my perspective I'm seeing a lot of
adoption use cases vary uh so depending
on the risk acceptance and tolerance
level I'm seeing good amount of
adoption. Okay. Yeah, I'd say we're
seeing um um you know a lot of customers
at different parts of the adoption care
but broadly speaking I'd say 2025 maybe
was the year of experimentation still
trying to figure out whether this thing
work how much is the holination rate you
know what what is it that you're getting
in terms of accuracy can you really
trust the outcome 2026 has been more
they are really proving ROI and and
seeing that AI actually is driving ROI
at scale and then as we're going through
towards the rest of the year I see more
and more really using AI for true
business transformation. Um so I said
broadly I agree with the direction. Um
though I would say um the exact
percentage isn't really I think relevant
whether it's 70% or 90%. And I don't
think the number of agents is really the
the right metric to look at but really
like what's the true business value that
you're ultimately getting uh from using
it these agentic AI solutions and more
and more we are seeing uh customers as
as you mentioned with the right data
foundation with the right security and
governance in place um to get into that
direction.
Adar.
>> Yeah, I would say that I think so far
enterprise AI adoption has been
underwhelming, but that trend will
change very very quickly and we're
already seeing it in 2026. And there's
two reasons for that. One is largely a
willingness thing, which is that for the
past 10 years, automation and business
transformation has just been pitched in
different forms. Everything from, you
know, BO, task mining, process mining.
So there's just a long uh there's like a
big graveyard of failed uh pilots and
initiatives there. So I've noticed that
a lot of enterprise executives are a
little bit hesitant about AI
transformation because it's one of those
things at least initially. Um and then
the second thing is just a capability
problem where the models just weren't
good enough until very recently. Um I I
think the big shift is the towards the
agentic paradigm where it's no longer
models for chat use cases. its models
for essentially being a co-orker, which
means managing many different
stakeholders, data sources, and
delivering economically valuable work
output versus being a personal
assistant. So, I'm optimistic about that
10% number or whatever number going up
very quickly.
>> Okay. Yeah. I think there are kind of
two two things. First, the definition of
adoption itself. I think there's a lot
of token maxing, a lot of people using
AIS personal agents as RA was talking
about. I don't quite think I mean that
is cons should be considered enterprise
adoption because a lot of those projects
are failing or low ROI but if you look
deeply at true kind of workflow end
to-end automation I think the 10% number
is probably right but it's growing fast
much faster than I would have expected
in fact in fortune 2000 there is a real
appetite now to go and kind of
agentically transform their businesses
so that's the first thing I actually I'm
actually more optimistic. I think we may
hit that 80% number even earlier than
2030. The second point is in it's it's
not it the where the adoption actually
uh kind of uh stops. It's not so much
technical anymore. It used to it was
technical I think last year few years
back uh it's 70% reason is
organizational. It's the change
management it's security infosc fear of
like unknown and so on. So I think if we
can kind of cross that chasm of
organizational resistance so to say
we'll see faster adoption.
>> So Sergey you make an interesting point.
What does adoption mean? I think the
other big question I have in AI is what
does success look like? Um I mean Anita
you talked about ROI. I mean when you're
out there talking to enterprises how are
they measuring ROI? What's interesting
to customers? Are they looking for
additional revenue? Are they looking for
cost savings? Is this really a question
of employee productivity? Where do you
think the most interesting uh value
that's going to be created for AI is
today that's resonating with
enterprises?
>> I mean ultimately when we talk about ROI
uh we always say there are two ways that
you deliver IOI. Either you help
customers make more money or spend less
money, right? Like so you want to either
increase productivity or help them
deliver additional revenue. Uh it is
extremely difficult to get to that
bottom line measurement. Um so companies
are using a variety of metrics or
leading indic um to measure that. Um you
know a lot of it started with adoption
as as so mentioned I think a lot of
mistake of
>> are we good
>> are we okay
she's making really strong points
[laughter]
[snorts]
>> the A's getting too excited about this
talk of AI
>> I think. Yeah. Let's continue and see if
uh
>> lot of companies now.
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, now we lost it.
Sorry for the technical difficulties
here.
>> All right, let's try we'll try going to
a different panelist [laughter] then
until we get Anita's mic working again.
Uh so Duncan, maybe you could talk a
little bit about um you know, how do how
do you all measure ROI and success
within HubSpot and are you bringing how
are you sharing that with enterprises
that you're bringing AI to? We try to
really stay focused on you know here
comes the new boss same as the old boss
which is outcomes at the end of the day
really understanding specifically what
are the business outcomes we're trying
to drive like we can look across say the
go to market journey and identify
whether it is you know a new qualified
lead into the top of the funnel it is a
closed one deal it is a customer support
ticket resolved successfully for the
customer and that brings a level of
clarity to how we build you know
obviously agents under that to deliver
those. It also lets you turn it into a
metric because if you can't measure it,
you're not going to be able to measure
success at all. And we found that to
work very well and basically paint the
picture for our customers of what's the
core highlevel uh outcomes are across
the journey. And then you can start
filling in the pieces along the way.
>> I want to bring it back to Anahita now
that hopefully her mic is working.
>> Yes, I believe this one is working.
Okay. uh we were talking about the how
do we measure ROI and I mentioned that
ultimately you want to measure the
impact on the bottom line but it's very
difficult because you know when you make
an improvement in one of your workflows
measuring what gets you there to
ultimately to the bottom line uh takes
time right so companies are using a
variety of leading indicators um you
know whether it started with adoption
and token consumption which was
certainly not a good use of um you know
ROI token maxing as so suggested it. Um,
but now it's more and more we are seeing
uh measurements of like the length of
workflow. Has it gotten shorter. I'll
give you an example. One of the agents
that we built for example shortened our
um the quarterly reporting from two
weeks to 48 hours or our earnings prep
from weeks of work to um just a couple
of hours of work or customer prep uh
preparations for from weeks to minutes.
So that's how we are starting to measure
uh productivity at the workflow level.
But uh I expect as more and more we get
to full automation and full workflow
transformation we should be able to see
full impact on the bottom line.
>> Yeah I think another key part of uh
getting AI getting our out of AI is
simply actually getting AI into
production and Dar in your talk you
mentioned how most enterprises are
actually failing in getting AI out off
the ground. You know Gartner says that
50% of geni projects fail. In your
experience at DAR, why is that? Is it a
technology challenge? Is it the
technolog is not good enough? Or do you
see it as an organizational adoption
where this technology is so new,
organizations are still figuring out how
do I actually deploy this?
Yeah. So, I would say there's a couple
of things. So, the first one is just the
actual confidence in the fact that the
AI is performing the way you want it to.
And our thesis there is just that most
of these enterprises don't have robust
evaluations that are agentic, meaning
they have the task, the trajectory, the
context, the artifact, and the verifier
across all of it to make sure that you
actually know the agent is doing what
you want it to before it hits any
production context. So that's the first
thing. The second thing is for AI
adoption to be successful, you just
can't hurl software over the fence. Like
it needs to come with change management,
cultural changes, all of these different
things. So, it's actually a little bit
involved, which is why you're seeing a
lot of the labs spin up their own deploy
codes with these FTEEs and partners with
these consultants and all of this sort
of stuff because doing a business
transformation when your whole culture
is like not AI forward, not technology
forward is really really hard. Um, and I
anticipate that more of those involved
end-to-end full stack deployment efforts
will uh increase the amount of AI
adoption and successful pilots.
>> And Serg, how about you? What's been
your experience when you're talking to
enterprises when it comes to actually
helping them get AI off the ground?
>> Absolutely. So uh giving a real example
one of our customers they have around
250,000 employees worldwide across 65
countries and they implemented our AI
employees for the entire hire to retire
cycle process like sourcing recruiting
onboarding an employee all of their IT
need ITSM type things payroll questions
and also actually managing payrolls and
and so on. So AI employees taking
actions answering questions across
around 70 odd use cases and we did this
over course of three or four months for
them. Um the impact and and this this
came from top down. So the impact is
actually real. So from thousand
employees they had around thousand
people in their HR ops team. They cut it
down to almost 500 people. Okay. from
five days to resolve an employee
question to like five seconds or 10
seconds to average to resolve an
employee question. So real actual
productivity gain, real uh employee uh
kind of happiness gain. So they see a
20% increase in employee satisfaction
for all issues related to kind of
employee issues, employee questions and
so forth. So I think this kind of shows
that if there is a will it it can happen
but it required as others say a lot of
change management. The biggest change
management was training the employees to
kind of adopt to the new systems new
processes than rather than go back to
the old systems. Uh a very quick funny
anecdote 30% of the queries the
employees would do and this is their
CHRO told me and this is companies
called Wipro they're global professional
services company 30% request the
employees actually ask a human again
even though AI agents already answered
or resolved the issue resolved the
ticket so they were very curious what is
the issue so they did some survey and
focus groups apparently employees didn't
trust trust agents can actually do it.
So they wanted a human to confirm again
that this was correct. So over time
there's lot of education involved in
educating the employees to kind of adopt
an agentic solution.
>> Yeah, I love that you brought up this
question of trust. Do the users trust
the AI? And there's also this question,
should enterprises trust AI? Ra, I mean
you talked about this in your talk. Um,
what do you make of the security
challenges? Do you think AI is actually
trustworthy today? Is it trustworthy?
But we're still winning over enterprises
are still convincing themselves that AI
should be trusted and figuring how to
deploy AI securely. Would love to hear
your thoughts there.
>> Definitely see it trustworthy at the
same time trust but verify, right?
Coding became amazing because you're
able to verify verify programmatically
or maybe even deploy another agent to
verify. So the solutions where you're
able to do this uh both generate as well
as verify is where we are seeing
accelerated adoption. Um I'll use a
different example. sales. One of my
customers um his focus is I want my
sales team just selling everything that
they do before and everything that they
do after I want to be able to automate
with agents. He's able to
uh trust the AI to do the right research
to summarize the meeting prep and use uh
our notebook LM to create a podcast so
that they can listen on their drive to
the customer site. Right? So simplify
all of that and you're just having the
conversation well prepared have that
conversation and then post that you're
able to update the meeting CRM whatever
you need to do when there are solutions
in place that can help you verify we're
able to trust much more and it is also
about the people's own journey in how
they get to that stage of this providing
enough value so I can take some risk
here and I'll trust this content and
then go with it. Duncan, does that match
up with your experience running security
within HubSpot? How how have the rough
edges how have you experienced the rough
edges of AI and how do you make sure
that you're deploying AI securely for
your enterprise customers? Yeah, I mean
I think there's two sides to it. Like on
on the one hand, models sophisticated as
they are are just weights and code. So
like you know everything we've done for
a long time around trust and safety and
security like those practices all apply.
um including things like understanding
that different outcomes require
different levels of trust and how we how
we uh watch out for that if you will
along the way. I think it's also
interesting though that whilst we can
take these frameworks that we've had and
and and leverage them uh you know in the
LLM world on the other hand a bunch of
the conversation we've had here is all
roads lead back to highquality evals and
I think and I 100% think that is true
the challenge that I think is
underestimated is unlike a lot of other
change management or previous tech
transformations even like the cloud or
mobile we were really coming up with a
different way of doing things or
accessing things that was very easy to
gro like you could wrap your head around
what it was and I think that's much
harder with this transformation and so
if you take evals um that's not just the
new version of QA and test coverage like
this there's a skill around being able
to write good evals what a golden good
high quality golden sets look like and
so Merkor obviously does a ton of great
work in this space but that's a whole
skill that people need to learn in order
to be successful and figuring out how we
how we get people through that change I
think is critical
Yeah, I think eval is a great example
and actually leads into our next
question and I can open this up to the
panel more broadly. I mean besides eval
what are you seeing working for
enterprises who are successfully
deploying AI. Is there a specific use
case? Is there a specific model
architecture one model many models?
Would love just to hear from your all
experience. What are you seeing as some
of the early six signs of success and
what it takes to succeed with AI in the
enterprise?
>> I I I can take it. Unless you um what we
uh where we see most success today um
couple of areas of course customer
support uh employee experience employee
support which is kind of two sides of it
kind of support we see a lot of examples
of finance operations today invoice
processing AP
um and in and data extraction like
basically document related document
heavy use cases any document heavy use
cases I'm expecting icting the the
surface area kind of continuously expand
over time, right? So, and we are seeing
that once we get into a large
enterprise, they will ask for kind of
more help acent areas. Uh, in terms of
architecture,
um, everyone is realizing depending on a
single model is is not the way to go
because the models are kind of getting
better. uh there's a war of attrition on
models and I think the model layer is
going to be commoditized and open source
models are getting better. So for us for
example we use Emma fusion which is
which blends 100 plus models all
frontier models many open source models
and and customers can take advantage of
that but I think that it's some for kind
of model fusion is becoming standard
architecture choice uh of course you
know I'll I'll let others comment on on
other pieces
>> an add to that a little bit uh yeah so
broadly we're seeing it across multiple
functions across enterprises as so rigid
said customer support is a very highly
well- definfined uh workflow that we
have seen a lot of automation on that
finance similarly you know well-
definfined workflows uh especially
quarter close month close all of those
are like well- definfined processes that
needs to be followed highly automatable
um and uh we have seen a lot in go to
market teams sales because they're the
drivers of revenue when you increase
efficiency there you increase your uh
top line marketing because they're huge
budgets we are talking about and and
then customer support and finance as I
mentioned because those are like highly
automatable um solutions but we're
seeing it across different industries
across different verticals and across
different functions. Uh maybe one thing
I'll also bring back on that trust
question that you said. Um when we talk
about trust there are two elements that
we primarily focus on. One is can you
trust that the data is accurate and it's
u you know accuracy basically. So for
example if I ask um an agent what was my
Q1 revenue there's only one correct
answer and this is not a trivial
solution to a non-deterministic
technology uh by nature. So putting the
right guardrails and the right evals and
the right definitions in place to ensure
that you always get that accurate answer
and that you can trust this is highly
important for enterprise AI adoption
because ultimately if you want every
employee to use these agents as opposed
to humans to get basic questions answer
you need to make sure that there is
accuracy there um 100% of the time. The
other option is dashboards which by
default have that level of accuracy. Um
the second one is governance. So how do
you ensure especially for data agents
how do you ensure that the right people
can have access to the right data and
not beyond that all right you know when
you're opening up access to your
financial data across the organization
to your employee compensation data to
your performance data how do you make
sure that each sales account executive
only gets access to the portion of
revenue that they are supposed to see um
you know how do you ensure that each
manager sees the data for their own
employees but not their peers so those
are the two elements that we focus on
that I believe is non-negotiable for
enterprise AI adoption
Ralph, you guys are probably working
with some of the largest organizations
in the world. What's the Google
perspective? Where are you seeing some
of the early takeoff with AI and any
commonalities of success within your
enterprise customers?
>> Yeah, a lot to do with the employee
productivity really stemming from
finding the right information at the
right time uh for what you're trying to
do. Surfacing information is one thing
and then taking the action. uh what's
the benefit policy on something to
actually completing that action to
enroll for it right so we are able to
automate those extensively with the
Gemini enterprise product and on the
other extreme uh CIOS are going deep uh
I use the sales team example where
they're able to automate every single
task that a specific role is doing and
they're able to deliver that uh
exceptionally well now they're actually
measuring sales productivity
are they able to have more conversations
and are they able to close more deals
faster? So aside from the usual uh
employee delight and those kind of
factors as well. So we're seeing it
across employee productivity as well as
actual delivering business ROI. So Anita
I want to bring it back to something you
said actually it'll be a question for
Dar given what he was talking about
earlier. Um but let's talk about data
and let's particularly talk about
sovereign AI. Should enterprises keep
their data? Should they share their data
with frontier model providers? Um,
should enterprises run their own models?
I mean, the palunteer co recently argued
that AI model companies. They pose a
threat to most enterprises. Is that an
overplayed geopolitical angle or do you
think sovereign AI actually matters to
enterprises? I mean, Adar, you mentioned
earlier how you guys are going to the
enterprises. You're help enterprises
unlock using I with their data. What do
you view of sovereign AI? Do you think
you know when you look across the data
layer, the model layer, confidential
compute layer, what do you think it's
okay for enterprises to share versus
what should stay behind their their
firewall?
>> Yeah. So I think there's a couple of
moving parts to the question, but the
first thing which is um like how are
enterprises going to harness their own
data to make these you know model
deployments work? I very much you know
subscribe to the school of thought that
every enterprise is definitionally
idiosyncratic right like uh even for two
companies in the same space McKenzie and
Bane like each of them have their own
processes that make them special and if
they were exactly one to one the same
then neither of them would exist right
there would only be one entity that
subsumes both of them so I think the
implication for a lot of AI adoption and
deployment is that the hardest part is
encoding a lot of that unique secret
sauce of the company which is the
workflows processes and organizational
context into the actual model weights or
the harness. And it can be something as
sophisticated as a way that an insurance
company does underwriting or we all know
that like AI agents can review résumés
but you can't just deploy an agent to do
that unless the agent knows what is the
talent philosophy of that company how do
hiring managers of that company screen
for résumés and stuff like that. So that
in general the challenge of encoding the
company's specific context and
intelligence into the model into the
agent I believe is uh very very
challenging to get right and the most uh
important thing for these deployments to
to go well. Now the second point which
is about the sovereign AI like what data
is okay to share and so on and so forth.
We work with a bunch of companies who
are sharing what we call commodity
workflows with the AI labs. So a lot of
the AI labs are looking to just see how
well the models can actually like just
improve model capability in real
enterprise context. So for example um an
IT function, right? Like if you want to
make the agent really good at traversing
all of the different parts of your IT
stack, we can help anonymize the data,
do the identity scrubbing, put it in an
RL environment that's useful to the labs
for training. And that's like typically
a no-cost option for the average company
because we can generate on the order of
magnitude of seven or eight figures for
them by monetizing their data very very
effectively. Now the last thing which is
on the like uh open weights stuff. I
think there are going to be a bunch of
use cases for private models. I think
there's going to be a bunch of use cases
for open source models because it hits
the price performance curve a lot better
and the only way to figure out which one
is the right is eval. So,
>> so I'd love to get the uh model provider
view on this. Yeah,
>> you are one of those model providers.
Not to put you on the spot. Yeah. But uh
do you think the Palenter co is correct?
I mean should uh enterprises be sharing
their data with Google and other model
providers? Can they trust you all that
you'll use the use the data in the right
way and won't compete with them?
>> Yeah, you can absolutely trust Google.
>> Um
so building on what others are saying
right? So there is enterprise data but
depends on whether you can uh give that
data to the agent. It doesn't always
need to be in the model right so you can
give it in uh prompts you can give it in
uh context uh I view it as the best
context is the smallest context that
gets the job done right. So you you
actually can do a lot of things in a
sovereign environment using a frontier
model. um you have all of that control
and obviously the enterprise agreements
that we have we don't see the customers
data so as an enterprise that's a
sacrosang for us as well um frontier
models will continue to improve
and then customers understanding the
cost performance and latency and we
always try to be the best on this perto
chart uh the customers do and will use
variety of models and we try to provide
all the flavors for you have the Gemini
Pro, Flash and Flashlight to find the
right use case for the right model.
That's on how enterprise can keep their
data and still use frontier models. Uh
coming back to the open source models,
what that is doing today is it's
eliminating the cost of training for an
enterprise, but the cost of inference is
still a cost, especially compared to a
CPU and the newer workloads. you still
have a much higher marginal cost when
you're actually running the model. So as
an enterprise, you have to ask yourself
uh am I willing to invest in that capex?
Am I willing to invest in the people and
that capabilities to grow that over
time? Right? So there are multiple
elements to here to deal with when
you're thinking open source does not
solve everything. So you want to also
think about the business aspects and the
organizational uh expertise when you
think about am I doing it on my own.
>> So I love that you brought up open
source again and Sergey mentioned it uh
earlier. So to to close the panel out
I'd love to dive into this question on
open versus closed. If you follow X it
seems like open source has won the
hearts and minds of everybody on on X.
Is that what you're seeing within the
enterprise? do enterprises care about
open versus closed? If you think about
uh you know 5 years from now, who's
going to win uh the model battle within
the enterprise? Is it going to be open?
Is it going to be closed? Is it going to
be both? Um maybe Duncan, you can start
us off given you've actually built and
deployed AI systems. What's your view on
open versus closed? What are you using
internally? And do you think enterprise
customers care about either?
>> I think at the end of the day, what
enterprise customers care about is trust
and reliability. And it's all about how
do you solve for trust and reliability?
And that probably means you don't want
to have any single point of failure in
the critical path if you think of it as
an engineering system like even as a
business system. So I think driving the
right outcomes which are going to be
that balance of cost and performance and
reliability um and so forth and and
there won't be a single thing that is
the right one for any of those. So I
think we'll absolutely continue to see a
mix of those and we'll get more
sophisticated about the tooling that we
use to be able to bring those to bear
and again make sure we've got
reliability without any single point of
failure anywhere in the chain.
>> And Anita, I'd love to get your view
because I know Snowflake works has their
own open models. You work with frontier
model providers. What do you think the
future of AI in the enterprise looks
like?
>> We work with both and I'd say the future
is probably a combination of both. What
we are seeing today is like frontier
models uh so far has been you know the
more innovative models. They're a bit
ahead of everybody else. They're pushing
the boundaries of technology and
innovation forward. Open source models
give you better cost, gives more more
brings more competition and increases
innovation as a result of that and gives
you better auditability and visibility
into what's happening uh under the hood.
Um and I think like for different
workflows you probably need different
one of these models, right? Like if
you're just simp simply summarizing an
email, you you probably don't need the
most advanced reasoning model. uh
whereas there there may be certain tasks
for which you actually want the most
advanced reasoning model and so I'd say
the the future is really um providing
both of them to customers and helping
them dynamically route the queries uh to
the right model and and that's what
we're doing um at Snowflake providing uh
that flexibility to the customers to
optimize at the query level for the
right model that they want um to use for
that specific use case.
>> And Serge, I'm going to let you close it
out because you mentioned open source
models. You said you think 40 50% of
your or your internal work is open
source. What what's your view on where
open source is headed versus Frontier?
>> I I agree with Anita. I think the the
question is about the strategic question
is can you change your model? It's not
open source versus closed source. And if
you change your model, do you need to
change your entire stack? Will it break
apart, fall apart? Do you need to code
everything again? Uh if you to build
correctly, you should build in a way
that you can change your model or you
have some kind of a model blender, model
selector underneath your agentic
orchestrator so it can take advantage of
all the innovations that are happening
in the model world without kind of
waiting for kind of retraining your your
entire agent layer. That's I think will
be the kind of the core architecture
going forward. However you implement it.
Well, thank you esteemed panelists. I
learned a ton and uh I'm really excited
to have a deep conversation today within
uh within this great campus about
enterprise AI. So, thank you.
>> Thank you.
All right, we uh we are running a bit
behind. So, we're going to power through
uh onto the next session. And uh it's my
privilege to introduce our next uh two
uh um presenters who are going to be
doing a fireside chat. So, uh, it's it's
my pleasure because I've had the
opportunity to work with Ali and Andy
for over a decade now since NA first
backed Data Bricks, uh, back at the
series, uh, series B back in 2014. Um,
so I'd love to introduce both of our
next speakers. Uh, first off, Ali is a
CEO and co-founder of Data Bricks. He's
responsible for the growth and
international expansion of the company.
He previously served as a VP of
engineering and product management
before taking the role of CEO in January
2016. In addition to his work at data
bicks, Ali also serves as an adjunct
professor here at UC Berkeley and he's
on the board at the UC Berkeley's rise
lab. Ali's was one of the creators of
the open source project Apache Spark and
his ideas from his ac and uh he has uh
he does research in areas such as
resource management and scheduling and
data caching which have been applied to
Apache Mezos and Apache Hadoop. Ali
received his MBA from Mid Sweden
University in 2003 and his PhD from KTH
the Royal Institute of Technology in
Sweden in 2006 in the area of
distributed computing. His co-founder
Andy Kowinsky is also the co-founder of
LD as well as perplexity. His work spans
research in real world impact in
artificial intelligence, data and
software infrastructure. He got his PhD
in computer science also from UC
Berkeley where he contributed to Apache
Hadoop and co-created Apache Mesos and
Apache Spark. He also co-ees the PhD
seminar on research to startups here at
Berkeley. Join me in welcoming both of
these amazing speakers and founders to
the stage.
>> Where do we sit? M
the love seat here.
>> We should bring all the other data
bricks co-founders [laughter]
to fill the seats. I think we can sit on
the same couch.
>> Yeah. Okay.
It be like very cozy.
>> Yeah.
>> Do this.
>> All right.
>> Like on my living room at home.
>> Okay. This is fun. Hi everybody. Thanks
for coming to this summit.
Ali, should we kick it off with some
telling some stories about data bricks
early days or Berkeley?
>> We were in Berkeley earlier.
>> Yeah, whatever.
>> UK. Okay. So, you and I go back to 2009,
2010, 2009.
>> You got to Berkeley and there was an
email going out. I think it started with
Yan or Scott Shanker sending this email
to the Mesos group that's like here's
this here's this visitor. He's going to
be joining the team. And Mate and Ben
and I were like, oh, who's this elite
guy? and we were very insecure and who
was going to be first author still. So
we were like and and then he comes in
and he's jacked or like okay I hope we
don't have to arm wrestle for this first
author. Um so that was my some of my
formative memories of you being injected
into our research project and then you
went on to like dominant research
resource uh fairness DRF paper and just
become like a a mentor and then
basically one of my co-advisors. So
that's what I remember. What do you
remember?
>> Yeah, I remember a lot of fun stories.
Um you know it's uh it was amazing
years. 2009, 10, 11, 12 was kind of, you
know, UC Berkeley was at the frontier of
all these new algorithms for the new
computer. The new computer was the data
center and we're doing all this amazing
research and I remember like, you know,
there was you know there was a lot of
skepticism around you know AI uh machine
learning at the time we called it and
data centers and all of that. So yeah,
it was uh best years uh for me u you
know most formative years. Um my
favorite memory is probably when we had
started data bricks and um actually
there was this big debate should we run
the company out of Berkeley or should we
run it out of San Francisco and like
half of the founders wanted to move the
company to San Francisco and half of us
wanted to keep it here in Berkeley and I
remember we brought in the Do you
remember this?
>> I do. Yeah, I'm I think I was on the
Berkeley side.
>> Yes, I was in the Berkeley side too. And
then you I think called the mayor of
Berkeley.
>> Yeah. First, I think we met with the
chancellor. Yes. And then he said, "You
should talk to the mayor." And he
introduced us. And so we hooked up with
the mayor and brought him into our
office. Yes. Which was not a very nice
office. Yes. Because Berkeley doesn't
have great office space.
>> And he brought a lot of people with him.
I think it was like I was, you know, us
as a researcher. I was like, "Oh, these
are all politicians." And they came in
and they sat there and we pitched them
on algorithms, advanced algorithms for
scheduling. And I think the mayor just
fell asleep and just dozed out through
the whole talk and then woke up at the
end and came up to me and or you and
your hands I think.
>> Yeah. And then he said,
>> "I hope that one day I will have a data
brick in every home,
>> you [laughter] know.
>> Still hasn't happened.
>> Hasn't happened.
>> I mean, maybe Nvidia's most recent rack,
you know, it could be where we go
someday." Um, so the that those days
when we were here at Berkeley, they were
the most formative for me too. And there
was something magic happening in the air
or the water. What do you think it was?
And do do you think that it's still
here? Has it changed since then?
>> Yeah, I mean I live in Berkeley still.
Yeah, I think actually the city is
special and I think the university is
special. Um, actually before I came to
Berkeley, um, I did a bunch of posttos.
actually lived like more or less in nine
different countries and went visited
nine universities and lived like in
different places of the world and I
think Berkeley and UC Berkeley
specifically is very spe special and the
thing that's special about UC Berkeley
is that there's this kind of attitude
that you can change anything you can
question anything I mean academia has
that in general but UC Berkeley
especially has that and I think I
actually it was kind of a little bit of
a culture shock for me when I came to
the research group because the kind of
things we're working on I was like
that's not research we're not supposed
to do that and we're like no we're doing
it it's cool, it will have impact. I was
like, well, that's not that doesn't make
any sense. This is like a weird this is
a you're cheating here or someone. It's
like no, we can do anything. Like this
is like we're just here to change the
world. Um so I think that that's the
kind of spirit of Berkeley and I think
that's uh university has it but the city
has it and its history and you know um
and I think that's what make it special
and sometimes it goes a little bit
extreme like you know I think uh you
know but uh there's you know research
that has super high impact and then
there's some research that you know is
further out like I remember there was
like research on delay tolerant networks
and it was like oh but you know
obviously the internet is broken if we
want to do interplanetary communication
and we have to redesign a new internet
for interplanetary communication because
eventually we're going to colonize all
of the universe. So that was one of the
research projects here in networking. So
you know I I think it's like the the
aperture is really wide and it helps
people to kind of broaden that and
>> yeah I know that in the early days we
were operating systems and distributed
systems research group and we took deep
inspiration from BSD and I remember we
went through a couple naming iterations
with what became Messos in the end. And
one of the contenders I put forward was
the Berkeley cloud distribution BCD or
Berkeley cluster distribution named in
as inspired by BSD uh Berkeley systems
>> BDAS Berkeley distribution of something.
No, no, no. There was BDAS, which which
Yeah, badass. It was like the official
nomenclature. You have to pronounce it
badass. The badass stack. But no, this
was what I put forward for the name of
Mesos. I said we should call it BCD.
Yes.
>> And I don't know you guys, I guess you
might not remember. Mate, I'm I'm pretty
sure Mate and Ben both said no, no, no,
no. Like, who are we to like be so lofty
as to name ourselves like only one edit
distance from BSD? And I was like, well,
we're going to like build the more
impactful operating system is who we
are. Uh, so yeah, I I did not win that
vote. I think my was pretty good. Uh, so
>> that's the birthday spirit.
>> Yeah,
>> question the norms.
>> Um, that's continued at data bricks. We
most recently announced or we announced
many things every week but Omnigent and
is a big open source framework trying to
play at the harness or that is putting
forward a new kind of uh kind of router
for harnesses is how to think of one way
to think of it also we talk about open
eval which we can talk more about later.
So uh how has that played forward from
your perspective as the leader of data
bricks for so long now seeing that what
we carried from Berkeley in terms of
open innovation and that maybe uh sky's
the limit mentality still carrying into
data brick strategy.
>> Yeah I think open for us has been always
super important. So we always want to
open source standards open source
interfaces because it creates
communities and those communities become
very powerful. actually database would
not have existed as a company if it
wasn't for the Spark ecosystem because
the Spark ecosystem just was way bigger
than anything any of us would have done.
Um and um it's so it's a good both good
for the community, it's good for the
world, but it's also a good business
idea as well as data bricks has proven
out. So we just continue doing that um
you know and we do it in things that we
think are the most useful and will have
the biggest impact. So a bunch of years
ago we did ML flow. Uh and MLflow
actually people don't know but it's it's
it's 40 million downloads still a month
every month. Uh so you know billions of
downloads uh a year and um what was
that? It was like in the ML era machine
learning era. So say 10 years ago uh
people were obsessed by the best models
but it was just very hard for machine
learning people to iterate on the um on
the different models. Uh so they needed
sort of a sort of a git version control
kind of a way to uh be able to iterate
and keep track of all the different
experiments. So that was MLflow. Um
Omniant which you just mentioned
recently that came from you know there's
just so many harnesses out there and
unlike large language models large
language models people switch between
them quickly. They're stocastic. Every
time you ask them a question they give
you a different answer and we can see it
in the databicks data because we serve
all the different models. We serve
actually proprietary models and open
source models. We have like data on all
of that and we see that people quickly
switch between them. So when there's a
new proprietary model or a new open
source model, people quickly within days
are moving to it. We've never seen
anything like it. You know, anything
else in software is sticky. You stick
with it, you know, and there's a decay
and people slowly churn and migrate, but
it takes a while. You don't just
instantaneously everybody just
flip-flop. Uh with with LM that is the
case. But what we saw with harnesses was
that people are building harnesses on
top of them. And the harnesses are kind
of like old software in that they lock
you in and you get used to the interface
and the memory and key sort of shortcuts
and all of that. So we wanted to create
something that lets you actually switch
between these and have it be completely
open and um so we the idea was a meta
harness so harness of harnesses. So it
will work with your cloud code, it will
work with your codecs, it will work with
any actually of them, open code, pi, you
name it. Um, so that way you can get the
multiplexing, you get the community and
the project has we we just launched it
this summer and you know I think just in
the first couple weeks we had a thousand
forks on GitHub. So it's really taken
off and over hundreds of people
contributed immediately within weeks.
Um, so you know we're very excited and I
think we're going to continue putting
out open source projects like this. I
think open source is actually have a
huge boon in the next bunch of years
thanks to vibe coding or AI because
before it was like okay it's it takes
huge amount of effort for a Linux
Torvalds to build a whole you know
operating system and compete with say
Windows um and at some point someone has
to pay his salary so they get hired by
companies and so on but today since the
cost of writing software is going down I
actually think it's going to be uh much
more palatable we're going to see many
many more open source projects out there
that become standards
I have a theory. It's not not really
here nor there, but it feels like we're
going to get a GitHub version where
instead of pull requests containing
code, they're going to just contain the
the prompts and then the the PR
reviewers will decide will like run
those prompts. And I think we're like
moving towards that in things like open
claw and and probably spark uh in that
the work on the committers is now much
more about deciding how much of the the
code was written by a human or how
deeply like how many hours did a human
spend on this pull request. Uh I don't
know gets me thinking about all the big
different the the big ways that the
world you and I grew up in and we
started data bricks in is like
fundamentally going to be different
going forward. any reflections on kind
of the paradigm shifts as they play out
for data bricks or I don't know the
future of software dev and vibe coding.
>> Yeah, I do think we're going more and
more towards you know if you can specify
what the program should do and you kind
of have the testing foundation and
harnesses then the implementation
actually doesn't matter. Uh the AI can
figure out the fastest the best
implementation of it. um and you might
be rewriting it many many times but it
really requires you to have this really
uh sort of airtight way of specifying uh
the the the code and I think it's moving
that way.
>> Yeah, that reminds me of evals. So you
we at data bricks recently announced the
uh this effort where we internally
scraped a bunch of our own coding issues
and uh tasks. We we've like built a data
set very large data set. How many over a
thousand? Yeah, it was it is a huge data
set of you know because we have about
4,000 engineers that are writing code
every day and so you know and and and
the whole company about 11,000 people
are submitting questions like you know
data science questions they want to know
how the business is doing they're
working in the field so we took all of
that
>> and that's like a basically a
declarative spec like you've
declaratively put into these questions
and answers I assume yeah that people so
people ask the question you have like
the data bricks answer and now you've
got this specification for a thing that
an agent could come and learn to do to
to answer like here's a bunch of
questions we wish our agents could
answer that's a bespoke evaluation or
benchmark to data bricks and uh do you
think that other uh enterprise tech
companies or just wider enterprise
companies are doing this and I have I
actually have a lot of opinions about
eval so we can deep we can dive into
this
>> yeah I mean I just think that there's so
much contamination happening so we
wanted to just have this you know ground
truth there's like every day there's
something released so we wanted to ask
the ground truth for us um which model
should we use and can Can we just use
GLM 52? Is it going to be as good or is
it not? And so on. So that's what we
kind of set out to do that. In general,
um the frontier labs are so obsessed
with, you know, super intelligence and
the march towards super intelligence
that um many of the things that we want
to do every day um are not kind of part
of their evals. So you know, they're
focused on HLE, humanity's last exam. Uh
and HLE has like these very complicated
math questions and physics questions. Uh
but when we actually looked at very
basic tasks that we wanted to do every
day um they weren't actually doing so
well on it. Actually the on the hardest
ones they were getting like 40% right.
Uh sorry 20 20% right and then on you
know the average ones maybe 40% right.
And these are like basic questions like
here is 1940s budget of United States uh
just get us what's what was the spend on
defense bud defense spending. So it
needs to kind of scan the PDF and figure
out how to present the things in the 4Ds
and do that and yeah it's like turns out
that's really hard u because you know
the focus has been on physics and math
things that you can RL like that not
these mundane enterprise or business
tasks. So we came up with this um uh
eval that we call office QA from you
know office the movie you know TPS
report. So we thought like let's just
solve that uh and uh so we're focused on
that and with that we were able to
basically build an agent that could do
the PDF parsing and do those kind of
things and get uh close to 80% uh
correctness on it. Um so I think evas in
general and specs are going to be
extremely important going forward. You
you've yourself uh you know launched a
bunch of these things terminal bench was
started by lud.
>> Yep. Yeah. So we teamed up with a
professor at Stanford Ludick Schmidt
whose group had done big stuff like clip
and uh this data comp set of projects
which was big in eval data that
basically data comp that Ludig had done
before was where you fix instead of uh
changing the model and then holding the
data set fixed you hold the model fixed
and and the agent and you change the
data set and have a leaderboard for that
to see how like how by changing data
sets can you improve the results of a
for one fixed agent. So Ludig was big
innovator in benchmarks and at Stanford
and I met up with him at Nurups and
actually that was the Nurups where we
launched this thing called the Commons
key prize which was
>> K prize.
>> Yeah, the K prize. Yeah,
>> get a million dollars.
>> Yeah, get a million dollar from me. I'll
write you the check. Uh I tweeted it on
stage at Nurips. This uh this like
promise that I'd write a million dollar
check to the first team who got 90% on a
thing that we called Swebench
contamination free. And that was
basically uh you have software engineers
write their agent code on some test set
which is just we scraped new GitHub
issues and we said here are these issues
that were from popular repos like
PyTorch or Spark or something. Your
agent has to fix these. Um normally
agents can tr people can train their
agents on the test set if the test set's
published. So you can do two things. you
can keep this test set secret um and or
you can say that you're not going to
scrape the test set until after all all
those tests are sub the the submissions
have been placed. So that's what we did.
uh you basically made a cut off date by
which people had to submit their agent
code and then we scraped new GitHub
issues for the four months after that
and then ran the evaluations on the uh
the agents that had been submitted and
the results were I guess around 10%
success rate which is [clears throat]
really good for new benchmarks
>> and with coming off of that launch and
then talking to Ludwig about his
>> isn't it crazy that like everything is
90% saturated but like when you do a new
one it's like 10%.
>> Yeah. And it starts this cycle, this,
and this is a new thing we're working on
too that we just announced a couple
weeks ago. It starts this what I think
of very inefficient cycle of every
benchmark, you mostly throw away the
last benchmark and start over from
scratch. And it turns out that we like
we did terminal bench one and then two
and then 2.1. And from two to 2.1, we
were mostly like fixing five to 10 tasks
that people had discovered were
essentially unsolvable. But a lot of
benchmarks don't even do those little
minor version releases where they update
the task to they update all these broken
tasks. And so there was this this
culture of uh or this like this shadow
culture. People who knew terminal bench
2 really well knew that like 83 was
actually 83% was actually 100%. Because
there were these unsolvable tasks and
you don't want that if you're a
benchmark maker. You want 100 to be
achievable but just be really hard. So
we did 2.1 and that gave us this idea
that hey benchmarks the way we're doing
them right now is really stupid. Uh it's
this like fame race and a hamster wheel
wheel where you do 2.1 and then we did
2.1. People don't even usually do minor
versions but then you do three and
terminal bench 3 would have a whole new
set of tasks with almost no overlap with
terminal bench 2 and instead we should
write benchmarks like software which is
you don't throw away the codebase every
time you do a new version of spark. You
like just make changes to the codebase.
YouTube fix bugs and you in terms of
benchmarks you delete the old tasks that
are saturated like now everybody gets
these right so don't keep them in the
benchmark anymore and add 10 new tasks
that are even harder and so it's a much
healthier thing because you're releasing
your benchmarks every two or 3 weeks and
>> it's like updating all the time
>> yeah like software
>> and it's like software and that makes a
lot of sense
>> and you're fixing bugs
>> yeah actually what I like about that is
like there's this good heart's law which
is whatever metric you use to evaluate
something ceases to serve its purpose
because it gets gamed. So this is
perfect. This basically make sure that
your benchmark because that's actually
what's happening. That's why everything
is 90% everywhere,
>> right? And so you can you can gently
steer it too because as the frontier
evolves, we just we discover that like
right now reward hacking is it's like
part of the major frontier. Nobody was
talking about reward hack. Very few
people were talking about reward hacking
a year ago. Now a lot of people are
thinking how new tooling is getting
built around it. the agents are getting
better at identifying it and we want
more tasks that are robust to reward
hacking or tasks that explicitly test
for an agent's resilience to reward
hacking. So we can do that in a week or
two is like come up with three new
tasks, cut a new version of the
benchmark. So terminal bench 3 on will
be like 3.1, 3.2, 3.3 really fast and
very relatively small uh you know
iterative updates. So pretty excited
about that. Um, I do believe that
benchmarks are changing dramatically and
I actually believe deeply in what you
said that the agent the the agent and
the harness code is going to be kind
optimized automatically more and more if
you have good eval. And so the that's a
pretty big change from early days like
lang chain or lang graph or these other
frameworks where you have humans
thinking hard about a good way to
architect your agent. Now instead you
have your humans spending all their
brain power coming up with the
evaluation. How do you accurately
capture like the distribution of hard
things inside your company or your you
know government whatever you're trying
to optimize and then you unleash these
optimizers either code optimizers or
prompt optimizers or model weight
optimizers or all of the above to just
hill climb those evals. So those two
trends together are where we're thinking
about with the harbor open source team a
ton right now at LA.
>> Makes a lot of sense. Uh I'm curious you
you with the open frontier
um is an initiative that you you know
you guys are spending a lot of money
basically helping open research open
science.
>> Um is that going to have a chance
against these frontier closed labs?
Yeah.
>> That are you know you know huge salaries
and then there's like you know very
secretive and there's no published
results versus this open frontier that
you're doing.
>> Yeah. Thanks for speaking at the meeting
a month ago. We assembled about a
hundred of the top researchers in AI
that are still doing open science and we
talked about the fate of science as we
know it. And one of the observations is
that many of the top minds are leaving
academia to go get paid go from their
400,000 $300,000 salaries to 1050$100
million salaries. go from having a lab
that gets 10 to 50 million in funding to
a lab that has billions and billions,
hundreds of billions in funding. And
those two key things, the access to
resources and the uh access to what is
now competitive salaries, which is
pretty insane for when we started data
bricks even 10 years ago. [laughter] Uh
I think just insane just in absolute
terms across the planet that we that
people are having billion dollar comp
packages right now. Um those are the
reasons that I I feel really worried
about uh science as we've known it and I
believe that innovation is necessary
right now to to create a new instit new
institutional dynamics that augment
academia and also create a proof of
concept for the ways that we can have
give researchers enough resources to
continue doing research at the frontier.
Um so yeah I guess explicitly to your
question of can they compete headon? No,
like we will never have a nonprofit
where the combination of philanthropy
and the US government, which is how
nonprofit research gets funded,
including this university we're sitting
at right now, uh where they will be able
to raise the hundreds of billions at the
same level as an anthropic or an OpenAI.
But they do need to raise one at least
one order of magnitude, maybe between
one and two orders of magnitude more
than they are. And that's just uh a new
like a new shape of fundraising and
probably a a new way of having labs team
up that they never really have had to in
academia. So maybe thinking about like a
lab of labs architecture. How do you
have more collaboration somewhere
between the way that academic labs
currently collaborate which is mostly
via reading each other's papers and
building off of ideas and the labs that
are in meta or openi and anthropic which
are centrally run all laser focused on
one single stack and one model. So
somewhere in between that is like a
looser but still aligned collaboration
of many labs that are doing evaluations
like Harbor or pre-training like Marin
the project at Stanford led by Percy
Lang or agentic frameworks like Graham
Nubic does at CMU or you know uh prompt
optimization and contextization like
mate Zaharia here or Omar Katab at
Berkeley and MIT. So you have faculty at
all the top labs plus independent
researchers doing nonprofits right now
is blowing up like not at the level of
uh anthropic but like a five or 12
person team just uh not even Neoab like
actual nonprofit not a for-profit and if
you can find a way to get the kind of
herd those cats and get first of all all
their faces on one slide then I think it
will and then second of all actually
operationalize that which is what we're
working hard on doing now like how often
do you meet how do you agree on artifact
Um, how do you get the models that Marin
is producing uh or collaborating with
the labs who are putting open weight
models like uh thinking machines or
reflections claims to be working on an
open model and to be releasing one
eventually soon. So, how do you team up
with these folks and get sort of the sum
is greater than the parts in a
nonprofit? Uh, that's what Open Frontier
is. And there's actually like a a kind
of big burst of momentum and energy.
We've been talking about it for like a
year and now um Sat Nadella tweeted
about like the need for this sort of
thing and data bricks is like showing
the way for the the possibility of this
open ecosystem actually standing a
chance. Uh and so I'm really passionate
about it.
>> Yeah, super super excited about it.
>> Uh how much time? One minute left. One
and a half. Okay. So we should talk
about undergrads because we're sitting
here at UC Berkeley. We both taught
undergrads here and mentored them and
brought some of them along with us to
data bricks. Uh you still pay hundreds
of engineers to do software engineering
to build frontier infrastructure. Is it
hopeless to come to Berkeley? I gave the
commencement speech here and a lot of
students were are super worried and
their families came up to me afterwards
and were like, "We're confused. What
should we do?" So is there hope? Like
should everybody just be bailing on
computer science?
>> Yeah. No, I think that uh I don't know
why this is happening. I think at the
frontier labs in particular, there's
this kind of sentiment that there's only
two more years of work left and then
everybody's going to be out of job in
you know and programming is going to go
away. Uh you meet more and more people
that feel that way especially in SF. I
think I don't know if that was also
going on in Berkeley or not but um you
know I think this is completely wrong. I
think the AI transformation will
actually take decades to go through and
it's just because it's it takes a long
time uh to change society like it takes
took from 1880 to 1920 when the electric
engine came about and it replaced the
steam engine before you could really
reap the benefits in society and
actually it took from 1880 to 1920
before they saw any impact on GDP and
it's not like okay that was a physical
thing it was hard no electric engine
already existed in 1840s 1850s so it
took just takes a long time same thing
with the PC revolution solution. It took
a long time and I'm at data bricks and
we have AI now and we're trying to
identify everything we're doing at the
organization and you just see how hard
it is that you have so many tasks that
have been built up over the last for us
we've only been existing for 13 years
some organizations out there have been
around 10 50 100 years takes a very very
long time to change everything you're
doing so I think that this agentic
revolution will take a decade at least
uh if not more uh and there's lots of
new good ideas like my favorite example
is internet already existed by 2000
Uh but it took uh Brian at Airbnb till
2009. So it took 10 years after internet
or even longer for him to come up with
that idea and that to take off. But the
internet was already there. People had
houses that they could rent. There was
nothing. There's no physical
infrastructure needed. Just takes a long
time to come up with good ideas and get
them to percolate and disseminate
through society. So I think that there's
most of the interesting things that are
going to happen haven't happened yet. Uh
there's going to be amazing companies,
amazing ideas, amazing research that's
been going to be created in the future.
Um you know, just as a couple ones that
I always like bringing up like I think I
think there's going to be a healthcare
company and it's going to probably be
worth trillions of dollars and that
healthcare company is going to be a
healthcare company where you can it you
know you can get a doctor that has seen
billions of patients and it can give you
personalized uh health care. People
would be willing to pay anything for
that, right? If you know if you could
help the the the health of you and your
loved ones or education. Education is
like super important to people.
Historically, VCs have always said, "Oh,
there's no money to be made in in
education." But I actually think, you
know, if you look at the United States,
elections are won and lost based on
education. And people care about the
education they give their kids. And this
this technology is transformative when
it comes to education. So, we're going
to see innovation there as well, both by
universities, you know, maybe
nonprofits, but also by companies. And
you could see people want to, you know,
if that if that's the best way to train
your kids, um, I think that that would
we're going to see that. So, there's so
many ideas. Uh, and I I can't believe
like this is the best time ever. Like I
would have I wish I was born so I would
have come out now when I'm like 20 25
now and start working on you know this
this is the best time if you want to
transform the world. Um if you came out
10 20 years ago things are more kind of
smooth. This big transformation is like
the best time to be alive and be part of
it. So I think computer science has uh
you know far to go and I think we're
going to see way more software being
written in the future than we've seen in
the past. So I'm super super optimistic.
Yeah, I'm very parallelly optimistic. I
work with PhDs still at law in
partnership with the labs at Berkeley,
Stanford, MIT and other top
universities. And if you find the
students who ship something like they
launch a thing, an open source project
or tweet one of their their papers or
something and they get a large uh
response to it, they still feel that uh
and you talk to that student, those
students are really motivated by impact
the way we were back with Patter and in
the Patterson labs thinking about BSD
and the way that we could change the
world. And uh and I like I talked to
them about how why they would be saying
no to these two or five or $10 million a
year comp packages that where they can
go kind of disappear into one of the
closed labs where they're going to do
frontier research and shape the the way
that Claude works, but they won't be
able to talk about it. And uh it's for
the same reason still that those people
they get that the getting to work on the
problem you see as the visionary one and
a commitment to disseminating that to
like the whole world is more impactful
in the end uh even than the proxy that
this 10 million or $50 million check
represents that's also representing
impact but it's kind of a lagging
indicator. So I think it's it's
inspiring to me to see that these
students still identify with the kind of
core thing which is this is the best
time in the history of our species to be
a person who wants to build something
that people use and work at the frontier
of AI. It's a good way of putting it
like yes you can make a lot of money at
the frontier lab but you'll never ever
have the chance to have as much impact
also because this is just during this
transformation you could do things where
you know assumptions are changing new
ideas can flourish. Uh this is the time
to do that. So you should think about
that as well.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Good. I think we're well out of
time. So, thanks for the chat. This is
fun.
>> Likewise. Thanks. Thank you.
>> Hi everyone. Just as a reminder, make
sure to grab all your stuff. Don't leave
anything in the auditorium. um and sort
of reserve te or anything like that. Um
and we're on lunch. So, thank you